RICHARD RUTTO

Water Purification Specialist.

Address Eldoret, Kenya, 254

Phone +254700465379

E-mail ruttorichard13@gmail.com

Detailed oriented water and wastewater systems Technician with 9+ years of experience in water, wastewater and laboratory operation. Helped in installation of new wastewater and water treatment plant unit and reduce work place accidents through strict adherence to OSHA regulations and complying with all environmental health & safety and quality assurance requirements. Developed comprehensive maintenance and repair tasks for water and wastewater treatment systems including ground water wells, exterior clean-out holding tanks, lift stations and effluent tanks. Seeking to use skilled quality control inspection background to reduce the departmental operation costs.

Skills

Design, planning and renovating of sick units.

Excellent

Execution of preventive and general maintenance.

Excellent

Quality control and continuous improvement.

Excellent

Leadership and teamwork

Excellent

Work History

2023-01 - 2024-04

Water Purification Specialist.

SKA International Group, Kismayo International Airport, Somalia

- Operates water purification equipment which provides potable water.
- Enforce safety standards and conduct on-the-job-training.
- Administers chemicals into untreated water to disinfect, sterilize, deodorize, and clarify water
- Performs various duties to provide Water Supply services as assigned.
- Makes adjustments to the equipment based on guidelines set by the supervisor.
- Ensures compliance with all water quality standards and operational requirements.
- Follows established procedures and safe work practices at all times.

2014-09 - 2021-10

Water/Wastewater Lead Technician

Pacific Architect Engineers, US Embassy, Kabul, Afghanistan

- Facilitate the production of water for the client by operating and maintaining re verse osmosis or other water purification equipment.
 - Enforce safety standards and conduct on-the-job-training.
- Ability to follow technical instructions, establish equipment maintenance schedules and utilize Reference material to improve water mission.
- Supervise Water Treatment Technicians in the performance of their duties.
- Prepare work assignments, enforce work rules and distribute projects to section employees for completion.
- Making rapid, appropriate decisions to improve simple to complex problems, keeping safety a priority.
- Fosters positive employee relations and employee morale.
- Possess basic hydraulic and electromechanical operation and troubleshooting skills for water/waste water plant installation.
- Performing bio-chemical oxygen demand tests on both treated and untreated wastewater.
- Used coordination and planning skills to achieve results according to schedule.
- Proved successful working within tight deadlines and fast-paced atmosphere.
- Improved operations through consistent hard work and dedication.
- Created plans and communicated deadlines to ensure projects were completed on time.
- Participated in team-building activities to enhance working relationships.
- Managed on-site evaluations, internal audits and customer surveys.

2011-09 - 2014-08

ROWPU Operator

DYNCORP INTERNATIONAL, Kandahar, Afghanistan

- Performing, work activities associated with a Reverse Osmosis Water Treatment Plant.
- Conducting, frequent and periodic inspections of plant to detect malfunctions and initiates corrective actions.
- Maintaining accurate and complete records on plant operation and laboratory data.
- Participates in new worker orientation; Provides technical support and guidance for subordinates.
- Executing work and maintenance schedules, ensures that buildings, grounds and equipment are maintained in proper condition.
- Performing routine laboratory tests and collects samples according to set testing schedules.
- Reading and recording daily plant parameters and equipment readings.
- Makes adjustments to the equipment based on guidelines set by the supervisor.

- Performing preventive and emergency maintenance on all electrical and mechanical plant systems.
- Assists Utilities Maintenance staff as needed in the performance of their duties at the plant.
- Created plans and communicated deadlines to ensure projects were completed on time.
- Actively listened to customers, handled concerns quickly and escalated major issues to supervisor.
- Monitored company inventory to keep stock levels and databases updated.
- Identified issues, analyzed information and provided solutions to problems.

2004-10 - 2011-09 **Quality Controller**

CHANDARIA INDUSTRIES LIMITED, Thika, Kenya

- Evaluating the Test results and giving recommendations based on the deviations from the Expected results.
- Observing and complying with food safety, environmental, Health and safety regulations.
- Preparation of reports on key product Performance and recommendation on quality check in products.
- Followed quality standards and procedures to minimize errors and maximize customer satisfaction.
- Updated quality control standards, methods and procedures to meet compliance requirements.
- Provided observations, took measurements and performed tests at various stages according to quality control plan.
- Developed and implemented quality assurance improvements.
- Assessed incoming parts for adherence to production requirements.
- Calibrated tools and equipment to meet requirements.
- Inspected inbound and outbound products for compliance with established industry standards, company policies and procedures.
- Conducted employee audits to check production performance against process standards.

2004-08 - 2004-10 Process Technician

- Coordinating processing operation, monitoring process parameters, Meeting production targets, coordinating product quality control And storage of product, facilitating plant maintenance and plant Labor force management.
- Writing technical reports on plant and fleet maintenance.
- Conversant with PLC systems and computerized operations.
- ISO 9001:2000 and 1400 Management systems compliant.
- Collaborated with packaging technicians to determine product changeovers and equipment maintenance needs.
- Complied with safety rules and standards to maximize efficiencies while reducing accidents.

- Performed electrical and mechanical troubleshooting on equipment.
- Performed preventive maintenance on equipment during scheduled downtime.

Education

2007-07 - 2008-06 Diploma: Total Quality Management KENYA INSTITUTE OF MANAGEMENT

- Awarded Total Quality Management.
- Relevant Coursework Completed: Design for Quality, Strategic Quality
 Management, Customer Service Management, HRM, Statistical Process
 Control, Reliability Safety and Assurance Management, Research Project,
 Practice of Management Foundation of quality management, Quality
 systems and tools, Quality Information Systems, Business Research Methods,
 Procurement and Supply Chain Management.

2000-01 - 2002-01 Diploma: Chemical Engineering THE MOMBASA POLYTECHNIC UNIVERSITY COLLEGE

- Professional development completed in industrial chemical processes.
- Relevant Coursework Completed: Mathematics and computer applications, Industrial organization and Management, industrial chemical processes, Thermodynamics and Fluid mechanics, Reactor engineering and control, Unit operation Electrical science and electronics, Workshop technology and Practice, Engineering, drawing and material science, Micro Biology/Biochemistry/Physical and organic Chemistry.
- Member of engineering students' society.
- Awarded Diploma in Chemical Engineering.

2016-10 - 2016-11 RO Operation & Maintenance (RO Specialist I Certification: Reverse Osmosis Operation And Maintenance

David H. Paul, Inc - New Mexico USA

Accomplishments

- Documented and resolved preventive maintenance issue which led to increased productivity by 20%.
- Used Microsoft Excel to develop inventory tracking spreadsheets.
- Supervised team of 36 staff members in Chandaria industries limited.

Languages

English, Swahili

Excellent